<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A full confutation of the covenant lately sworne and subscribed by many in Scotland; delivered in a speech, at the visitation of Downe and Conner, held in Lisnegarvy the 26th. of September, 1638. Published by authority.</title>
            <title>Speech, delivered at the visitation of Downe and Conner, held in Lisnegarvy the 26th. of September, 1638</title>
            <author>Leslie, Henry, 1580-1661.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1639</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05345</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15497</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102367</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838152</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838152</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2515</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05345)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2515)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 805:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A full confutation of the covenant lately sworne and subscribed by many in Scotland; delivered in a speech, at the visitation of Downe and Conner, held in Lisnegarvy the 26th. of September, 1638. Published by authority.</title>
                  <title>Speech, delivered at the visitation of Downe and Conner, held in Lisnegarvy the 26th. of September, 1638</title>
                  <author>Leslie, Henry, 1580-1661.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 20 [i.e. 38] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by John Raworth, for George Thomason and Octavian Pullen, and are to be sold at the Rose in St. Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1639.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reissue, with cancel title page, of: Leslie, Henry. A speech, delivered at the visitation of Downe and Conner, held in Lisnegarvy the 26th. of September, 1638.</note>
                  <note>Page 38 is misnumbered 20.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Presbyterianism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2515:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2515:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A FULL CONFUTATION OF THE COVENANT, Lately Sworne and Subſcribed by many in <hi>Scotland;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Delivered in a Speech, at the Viſitation of <hi>Downe</hi> and <hi>Conner,</hi> Held in <hi>Liſnegarvy</hi> the 26<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> of <hi>September,</hi> 1638.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed by Authority.</p>
            <q>My ſonne, Feare the Lord, and the King, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>eddle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with them that are Seditious. <bibl>
                  <hi>Proverb. 24.12.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>For Rebellion is as the ſinne of Witchcraft. <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Sam. 15.23.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>John Raworth,</hi> for <hi>George Thomaſon</hi> and <hi>Octavian Pullen,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Roſe in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1639.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:2515:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2515:2"/>
            <head>After the names of the Clergie were called, the Viſitor ſpake in this manner;</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>ND now (my brethren of the Clergy, and all you Gentlemen of the Laity) I intreat your attention while I ſhall expreſſe my ſelf in ſome things that concern my Paſtorall charge. Some things I have to ſay that concern the Clergie onely, Some things that concern the Church-wardens, And ſome what that doth concern both the Clergie and the Laity.</p>
            <p>As for you of the Clergie, There is generally a great fault in you in the neglect of Catechizing: You know that you are bound to it by the Canons of the Church, bound by an act in my firſt Viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and though ye regard neither of theſe as I know many of you do not, yet conſider I beſeech you that ye are bound to it in conſcience; for Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chizing is the eaſieſt and moſt profitable way of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. The Apoſtle calls it <hi>the doctrine of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings of Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 6.1.</note> which muſt be layed before a man can be led forward unto perfection. It is milk for babes, whereas preaching is meat for men that are of age, who have their wits exerciſed to <hi>diſcern both good and evill.</hi> But you cannot abide to give milk,<note place="margin">Heb. 5.14.</note> and are all for ſtrong meat, albeit there are many of you who are not well able to chew it. This is the true cauſe of the ignorance of the people, for they
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2515:3"/>not having been inſtructed in the grounds of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, are not able to underſtand any part of a Sermon. It is one of the great ſtratagems of our adverſary the devill, that when he cannot draw men wholly from the ſervice of God, he makes them to ſingle out ſome part of it and to magnifie that with a neglect of all other parts; as namely Preaching amongſt you, which is grown to that eſteem that it hath ſhuffled out of the Church, both the publique prayers which is the immediate worſhip of God, and this duty of Catechizing: and is now accounted the ſole and onely ſervice of God, the very <hi>Conſummatum eſt</hi> of all Chriſtianity, as if all Religion conſiſted in the hearing of a Sermon. Unto whom I may ſay in the words of the Apoſtle, <hi>What? Is all hearing? Is the whole body an eare?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.</note> Or tell you in the words of a moſt Reverend prelate, That if you be the ſheep of Chriſt, you have no mark of his ſheep, but the eare-mark. And therefore to conclude this point, If you will will not hereafter make conſcience of this duty of Catechizing; Then the conſcience of my duty will inforce me to proceed againſt you according to the Canons of the Church.</p>
            <p>As for the Church-wardens I have a double com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint againſt them; One, That whereas by their place they are to look unto the fabrick of the Church, the greateſt part of your Temples are kept no better then Hog-ſtyes. I know that it is one of the myſteries of iniquity in their Religion, that God is moſt purely ſerved, when he is worſhipped ſlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly, in a poor and homely cottage: and that any coſt is too much to be beſtowed upon Gods ſervice. They are much like unto the officers of <hi>Julian</hi> the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2515:3"/>Apoſtate, who when they ſaw the ſtately veſſels of the Temple, cryed out, <hi>En qualibus vaſis miniſtratur Mariae fil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o?</hi> what ſtately plate is this for the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penters ſonne? But my ſecond complaint is yet greater. They are bound by their Oath to preſent all known diſorders within their Pariſh, eſpecially them who do not repair unto the Church to hear Divine ſervice, and to receive the Sacrament accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the orders of this Church; Yet they preſent none at all: And indeed the Church-wardens, eſpecially in the <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ds</hi> and <hi>Claneboyes,</hi> are of all others the moſt diſorderly men, the very ring-leaders of the ſeparation, and it is for that cauſe they are choſen, that others may not be preſented. So that it ſeems unto me that too many of them in Scotland have entred in a mutuall bond to defend one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other by Arms: So their fellows in this Dioceſſe have entred in a mutuall bond to defend one another by their Oathes. But, here I tell them plainly, that I will proceed againſt them, Firſt, for the neglect of the repair of their Churches, Next, for their non-conformity, Thirdly, for not preſenting notorious offenders, And laſtly, for their perjury. And if they think my authority too weak to overtake them, in regard of the great Patronage and countenance they have; I will deliver them over unto a Court that is able to deal with them.</p>
            <p>My laſt complaint will hold me longer. It ſtrikes both againſt the Clergy and the Laity, for their ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall non-conformity, and diſobedience unto the Orders of this Church. You of the Clergy have all Sworn, ſubſcribed and promiſed abſolute confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity; And yet when you come amongſt your people,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2515:4"/>you ſlide back, and for a colour of obedience, read ſome part of the Service, it may be the Leſſons, and a few Collects, as if it were left unto your power to mince the Service of God, cutting and carving upon it as you pleaſe. I muſt tell you that thoſe who will not be tyed, neither by oaths, Subſcriptions, nor promiſes; There is nothing will tye them, but a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercive power.</p>
            <p>But, they of the Laity are yet worſe, they will hear no prayer at all. While divine Service is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, they walke in the Church-yard, and when prayer is ended, they come ruſhing into the Church, as it were into a Play-houſe, to hear a Sermon. But ere it be long, I hope a courſe ſhall be taken, that they who will hear no prayers, ſhall hear no Sermon.</p>
            <p>I know that the thing which doth encourage you in this your diſobedience, is the preſent Inſurrection in <hi>Scotland.</hi> You think (and ſome of you do not ſtick for to ſpeak it) that they will inforce the King for to yeeld unto all their demands, and amongſt the reſt procure unto you a liberty to live here as you liſt: But deceive not your ſelves; for howſoever in <hi>Scotland</hi> ſome thinke themſelves ſtrong enough to reſiſt their Prince, yet (I thanke God) you are not ſo many here, but the Kings Laws and authority is well able to overtake you. And be aſſured that their inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent oppoſition againſt our moſt Pious Prince, will make you that are of their Faction to be more nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly look'd unto here, then otherwiſe you would have been: for now, that our neighbours houſe is on fire, it is high time to look to our own. And ſurely, methinks, that if there were in you, a ſparke of the fear of God, and of true loyaltie unto the King, the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2515:4"/>rebellious proceedings of theſe men would put you out of love with their Religion. For I perſwade my ſelf, that when you were firſt leavned with their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, you did little think that their aim was Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion; But did conceive (as ſometimes I my ſelf did) that they did all out of conſcience, and were men free from violence, or the leaſt thought of diſloyalty; But now behold their proceedings, and judge them by their fruits.</p>
            <p>You may perceive how that Sect ſince the firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of it (which is not much above Fourſcore yeers, in the Raign of Q <hi>Mary</hi> of England) hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from evill to worſe, by Six degrees. At firſt they did only manifeſt a diſlike of Epiſcopall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and ſome Ceremonies uſed in the Church of England, as liking better of the government of Geneva, which was deviſed by Maſter <hi>Calvin,</hi> and that cunningly enough for the ſtate of that Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, which being popular, could not brook any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther government of the Church, but that which is popular alſo. And yet I muſt tell you that Maſter <hi>Calvin</hi> wanted nothing of a Biſhop, but only the title. For the Church of Geneva is not a Parochiall, but Dioceſan Church conſiſting of divers pariſhes which make up one great Presbytrie, and he all the dayes of his life was moderator thereof; without whoſe conſent, no Act neither of Ordination nor Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction was done. And ſo likewiſe M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Beza</hi> for ten yeers after the others death, held the ſame place of government, untill <hi>Danaeus</hi> ſet him beſide the cuſhion, and procured the Preſidency to go by turns. In the next place from diſlike they proceeded to contempt of Epiſcopall government, and this (if
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2515:5"/>y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> will beleeve St. <hi>Cyprian</hi>) hath been the very be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of all hereſies and Schiſmes,<note place="margin">Ad Rog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ionum.</note> 
               <hi>Initia Haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> (ſaith he) <hi>&amp; or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us Schiſmar corum haec ſunt, ut praepoſitum ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o tum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re contemnant.</hi> And againe, <hi>Vnd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Schiſmata &amp; haereſes ortae ſunt niſi dum Epiſcopus qui unus eſt &amp; Eccleſiae praeeſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ad P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</note> 
               <hi>ſuperbâ quorundam preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione contemnitur: &amp; homo digratione Dei honoratus, ab indignis hominibus judicatur.</hi> In the third place from contempt they did proceed unto open diſobedience unto all the Orders of the Church; And (like thoſe of whom <hi>Nazianzen</hi> ſpeakes) would be pleaſed with nothing but what did proceed from their own devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, eſteeming him the holieſt man, who could find moſt faults. From diſobedience they did proceed unto Schiſme and open ſeparation, accounting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves only to be the brethren and Congregation of Chriſt and all others who are not of their faction to be the children of this world. From Schiſme they proceeded to hereſie; For it is moſt true which S<hi rend="sup">•</hi> 
               <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> did obſerve, that <hi>Omne Schiſma gignit ſibi haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin,</hi> Every Schiſme doth deviſe unto it ſelf a hereſie, ſome falſe doctrine or other to maintain their ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: And theſe men have deviſed not a few, and ſome that have been condemned by ancient Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels and Fathers, as namely, <hi>Epiphanius</hi> reckons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the condemned hereſies of <hi>Aerius,</hi> that he maintained there was no differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce between a Biſhop and a Presbyter, and that all ſet Faſts are unlawfull, Jewiſh and Superſtitious. And is not this the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of theſe men? But, laſtly their diſobedience Schiſme and hereſie have now drawne them into o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen Rebellion, and I wonder whither will they go next? For I am deceived if they have not yet a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2515:5"/>ther journey to go, and that they cannot ſubſiſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till they arrive at pure Anabaptiſme; From which they now differ but a little. And ſurely if any of you will read the Hiſtory of the Anabaptiſts, you will finde that their proceedings were a great deal more moderate, and Chriſtian like, then theſe mens are. This is the juſt judgement of God, that they who run out of the Communion of the Church, ſhould likewiſe run out of their own wits.</p>
            <p>I beſeech you therefore to conſider their wayes, and how that if you do not break off compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, they will ſhortly lead you into Rebellion. For mine own part I profeſſe that the firſt thing that made me out of love with that Religion (beſides their groſſe hypocriſie) was their injurious dealing with Kings, who are Gods Vice-gerents here upon Earth, which I obſerved both by their doctrine and by their practice, and I will now give you a briefe taſte of both. As for their Doctrine, you know they take from the King all authority in cauſes Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, and will not allow him to do theſe things which the good Kings of <hi>Judah,</hi> and the godly Emperours of the Primitive Church did. Yea, they will not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them to preſent or nominate a Miniſter to a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefice, nor to give a Vote in a Generall Aſſembly, except (forſooth) the King be a Lay-elder; nor yet to make any Law<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s concerning matters of outward Order and Politie to be obſerved in the Church: Nay, They have gone further, allowing Subjects to reſiſt their Prince by force of Armes, and in ſome ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to depoſe him, yea and to take away his life if he be a Tyrant, and though he be the godlieſt Prince in the world, he muſt be eſteemed a Tyrant, if it
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2515:6"/>pleaſe the Presbytery to declare him for to be ſuch. So that Kings ſhould be in a farre worſe caſe under the Presbytery, then ever they were under the Pope; For in ſtead of one Pope, they muſt be ſubject unto a thouſand.</p>
            <p>This is their doctrine. Now I will ſhew you their Practice, And firſt how they dealt with that bleſſed King <hi>James,</hi> while he was in Scotland. They did perſecute him in his mothers womb, and when he came unto ripe yeers, they ſuffer'd him not to enjoy one quiet day, by their Seditious practices: Of a great many I will cull out a few of their attempts w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> are moſt notorious; Firſt, when as the Ring-leaders of that Faction had concluded the ſtate of Biſhops to be unlawfull, they ſent their Commiſſioners unto the King, commanding him and his Councell under pain of Excommunication, to put them downe. Againe, A French Ambaſſadour being in Scotland, when he was to go away, the King commanded the City of Edenburrough according to the ancient cuſtome, to entertaine him with a banquet. This charge was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven on the Saturday, and the banquet to be on the Munday, and upon Sunday morning ſome of the factious miniſters hearing of it, to croſſe his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties deſignes, proclaimed a publick Faſt to be kept on that day, and becauſe that the Nobility, the Kings Servants, the Provoſt and chiefe Citizens of Eden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burrough, did by the Kings direction attend the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour, they proceeded againſt them almoſt unto the ſentence of Exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication. Afterwards when his Majeſty was taken priſoner at Reuthen, by ſome of his treacherous Subjects, intendig thereby to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2515:6"/>force his Majeſty to their owne ends: His Majeſty being happily delivered, did with the conſent of his three Eſtates in Parliament, declare that to be a trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable fact: But the ſeditious miniſters being aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in Synod, and taking themſelves to be the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame Judicatory, did pronounce that Treaſonable fact to be moſt juſt and lawfull, threatning with all the ſentence of Excommunication againſt all who did not ſubſcribe unto their judgement therein. They did uſually inveigh againſt the King in their Sermons, and rayle at him io his face, for to bring him in hatred with his owne Subjects; And when ſome of them were convented before the Councell-boord for ſo doing, they declined his Majeſties au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, alleadging that he was no Judge over them in Church-matters. They uſed ordinarily to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime Faſts without the Kings privity, eſpecially when ſome factioners were about to attempt ſome great enterprize againſt the King: And then the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters were taught all to ſing one ſong, crying out upon the abuſes of the Court and State, whereby they ſet the people a madding. All this you may read more at large in the Kings declaration printed Anno 1585. I will now adde ſome other of their practiſes that come within the compaſſe of my own remembrance. When the Earle of Bothwell was in the act of Rebellion againſt the King, and had divers times attempted to take away his Majeſties life, there were great gatherings in Scotland for the relief of Geneva, then ſtraitly beſieged by the Duke of Savoy; The Miniſters who were the Collectors, gave a great part of it to maintain the Earle in his rebellion againſt the King. Afterwards when the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2515:7"/>
               <hi>Gawries</hi> conſpired againſt his Majeſty, and he mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſly reſcued by the vaſour of his Servants; his Majeſty deſired that there might be a publick thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving in all Churches within the Realme for his deliverance; But divers of the miniſters, the ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaders of that faction did refuſe, and did plainly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuate that they did neither beleeve the King, nor his Nobles, nor his Servants who were witneſſes; that ever there was ſuch a conſpiracy; But that it was a plot of the King to murder the <hi>Gawries.</hi> I ſhall not need to tell you of the 17<hi rend="sup">th</hi> day of <hi>December:</hi> Therein none of you who hath not heard in what feare and danger of life the King was then, by an inſurrection which was raiſed by the ſeditious Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of ſome of theſe fiery preachers. One thing I cannot omit, how that they called a Nationall Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly to be held in <hi>Aberdeen,</hi> the King ſuſpecting the event (as he had good cauſe) and having long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by Act of Parliament all Authority in cauſes Eccleſiaſticall, and particularly for calling of Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, declared to belong to his Royall Perſon; He ſent to inhibit them by open Proclamation, but they would not deſiſt: whereupon being queſtioned, they declined the Kings authority, contrary to the Lawes of that Ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gdome; for which they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dired, found guilty and condemned of Treaſon. Yet that mercifull Prince did neither take life nor goods from them; But only baniſhed ſix of them: And when ſome of theſe could not live abroad, upon the acknowledgment of their offence, he not only gave them leave for to returne, but alſo provided livings for them, And yet one of theſe who holds both his life and his living by the Kings mercy,<note place="margin">Dr. Sharp.</note> is at this day
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2515:7"/>a principall Firebrand in this Rebelli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n. And thus they uſed King JAMES, which occaſioned him in that golden Treatiſe intituled <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to proteſt that he had found more truth and honeſty in the barbarous high-land-men, and bloody borde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, then ever he did in the men of that Faction.</p>
            <p>Thus have I given you a brief taſte both of their Doctrine and Practice, concerning the oppoſing of Princes. But here leſt this ſhould be thought a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall ſinne, and ſo Jeruſalem upbraid her ſiſter Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria; I will ſhew unto you, that they of this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in England had been as deep in this condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but that (God be praiſed) they had not ſo much power. And beſides that, ſome there have ſuffered death for their ſeditious practiſes againſt authority, in ſeeking to bring in their new Diſcipline, as <hi>Hacket, Coppinger,</hi> and others: You may judge of the inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and deſires of the reſt, by their writings. One of them who wrote a Book, intituled, <hi>A Dialogue of whice Devils</hi> (which was a moſt fit Title for theſe mens Books, for if ever there were white Devils, or Devils transformed into Angels of light, it is in their perſons, who under the pretence of Sanctity, labour to bring in all manner of diſorder into the Church, and confuſion into the Common wealth) That Author ſayes expreſly, that <hi>If Princes do hinder the bringing in of their Diſcipline, they are Tyrants, and being Tyrants they may be depoſed by their Subjects.</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, who calls himſelf <hi>Stephanus Junius,</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Miles &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Is is lan full for the people by force of Arms to reſiſt the Prince, if he hinder the building of the Church.</hi> A third railes at Queen <hi>Eliſabeth,</hi> for exerciſing that lawfull Authority in cauſes Eccleſiaſticall which was united
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2515:8"/>unto her Crown; reſembling her unto all the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Kings, and others who took upon them unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to intrude themſelves into the Prieſts office: as unto <hi>Saul</hi> for his offering of ſacrifice; unto <hi>Ozias</hi> for his burning of incenſe; Yea, and to <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu</hi> for their offering of ſtrange fire. It is well known how that <hi>Martin</hi> in his firſt Book threatned fiſts. And the Authour of the ſecond Admonition, ſayes plainly, that <hi>There is many a thouſand that deſire the ſame that he doth, and that great troubles will come of it if it be not proviaed for.</hi> Another of that crew, directing his ſpeech unto the Biſhops, ſaith, that <hi>The Presbytery muſt prevail:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Demonſt: of diſciplin in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face.</note> 
               <hi>And if it come to paſſe by that means that will make your hearts to ake, then blame your ſelves.</hi> I could preſent unto you a great deal more of ſuch ſtuffe: but I will onely alledge one paſſage of Maſter <hi>Cartwright,</hi> whom for his learning I honour far above all that ever were of that faction, he ſaith that the Church is not in the Common wealth, but the Common wealth in the Church, and therefore, as a wiſe man will not frame his houſe to his hangings, but his hangings to his houſe: So the Church is not to be fitted unto the Common wealth, but the Common wealth unto the Church. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon it will evidently follow, that as in his opinion there ought to be a parity in the Church, ſo likewiſe a parity in the Common wealth: ſo that it is more then manifeſt that the thing which they aime at, is to have no King at all. And therefore it is remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, how that the Traitour <hi>Calderwood</hi> in his bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphemous Book, called <hi>Altare Damaſcenum,</hi> doth not onely rail againſt King <hi>James,</hi> charging him with perjury &amp; perſecution, but alſo doth inveigh againſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2515:8"/>all Kings whatſoever, ſaying, <hi>Naturâ inſitum eſt o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> reg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bus in Chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um odium.</hi> It ſeemes this mad deg did not remember Gods promiſe made un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Church, That Kings ſhould be her Nurſing-fathers, and Queens her Nurſing-mothers: And God who is never worſe then his word, hath made his promiſe good; for never were there ſo great In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments for the propagation of the Goſpel, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement of Chriſts kingdom, and the procuring of the peace of the Church, as Chriſtian Kings have been; and amongſt them all, never any more then our moſt gracious King that now is, and his moſt renowned Father, whom thoſe men did ſo much oppoſe and traduce.</p>
            <p>But what do I need to remember matters of old: for the Children are worſe then the fathers, and their preſent practiſe now in <hi>Scotland,</hi> doth ſurpaſſe all the in quities of their Fathers, and will make them to bee forgotten. Now Biſhops and conformable Miniſters, whoſe perſons had wont to be eſteemed ſacred, are ſtoned, beaten, wounded, and drag'd out of their Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits: a thing which was never uſed by the Heathens againſt their Prieſts, of what lewd condition, or quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty whatſoever. And yet thoſe are they who ſweare to be good examples to others of all godlyneſſe, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berneſſe, and of every duty they owe to God and man. Now what Godlyneſſe, Soberneſſe, or righteouſneſſe hath been in ſuch proceedings, the like wherof hath not been heard amongſt the heathen; Let all the world judge. Before they had wont to aſſault us onely, with their tongues which are ſharper then arrowes, and with their pens which are as light as Geeſe quils: But now they are come (as <hi>Tettullian</hi> ſayes) <hi>A ſtilo ad machaeram,</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:2515:9"/>from words to blowes. That we may ſay with <hi>Bernard Leones evaſimus ſed incidimus in Dracones.</hi> We eſcapd the mouthes of Lyons, but have fallen into a den of Dragons; for theſe ſure are Ceraſtes, Fiery flying Dragons. But would to God their madneſſe had ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed here: They have not onely done wrong unto Gods Prophets; but alſo touched his annointed, entring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a mutuall league and covenant againſt him, arming his Subjects, taking Oathes of them to maintain their cauſe, blocking up his Caſtles, refuſing all his Majeſties moſt gracious offers for peace, and indeed proclaiming a plain defiance unto him. Good God! Can they be Chriſtians that do theſe things? Or have they any warrant for this out of Gods word which commands us to be ſubject to Superiour powers, and that for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſake, even then when all Kings were enemies unto Chriſtian Religion? Or have they any example for thoſe proceedings out of Pious antiquity? The Chriſtians in the Primitive Church when they were led as ſheep to the ſlaughter all the day long, and ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the moſt exquiſite torments that could be deviſed; Yet would never take Armes for to reſiſt the Prince; but put on this reſolution, <hi>Arma noſtra preces &amp; Lachry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae.</hi> Yea, when theſe perſecuting Emperors, had oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of warre againſt the barbarous nations, the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians were the Emperours beſt and moſt faithfull Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, ſo terrible unto their enemies that they were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the thundering Legions. And S <hi>Auſtin</hi> doth high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commend them for their faithfull ſervice, unto the heathen Emperours, who did moſt cruelly ſpill their blood, onely for their profeſſion of Chriſt. And let no man ſay, it was for want of power, that they did not defend themſelves by armes; for it is well known,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2515:9"/>that if they had thought it lawfull to reſiſt the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour by Armes; they were of that number, power, and reſolution, that they had been able to have ſhaken the foundations of the Empire. But now it ſeemes that theſe men of whom I ſpeak, have learned another Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity, and think that they are bound to ſtand to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of their dread Soveraigne, the Kings Majeſty, his perſon and authority, in the defence and preſervation of the true religion (as they have expreſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d in their late Printed confeſſion of faith, wherunto they have ſworn) ſo that they do plainly inſinuate, that they are no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bound to defend, the Kings perſon and authority, then he doth ſtand in the defence of the true Religion; And that onely muſt be accounted the true Religion, which they themſelves do beſt like of: If the King will not maintain that, then for all this laſt Oath, they are freed from their Alleigance, wherein they have more then juſtified the Ieſuites in all their rebellious practiſes, and the Ieſuites can well tell how to take ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage thereof: for it is not long ſince a Ieſuite wrote a Book, in the defence of the Loyalty of their Order, alledging that Proteſtants had allowed the rebellion of Subjects againſt Princes, as much as any of their Order had done, and gives inſtance in <hi>Buchanan, Knox,</hi> and <hi>Goodman.</hi> But <hi>Andreas Rivetus</hi> a Profeſſor of <hi>Leiden,</hi> anſwering the Ieſuite, doth profeſſe, that all Proteſtants do condemne that doctrine, and aſcribes the raſhneſſe of <hi>Buchanan</hi> and <hi>Knox, Praeferbido Scotorum ingenio &amp; ad audendum prompto</hi> And now it feares me, that ere it be long another Ieſuite ſhall publiſh a Book to prove that the preſent inſurrection in <hi>Scotland,</hi> is a greater re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, then was the Papiſts Gun-powder-plot: in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard that the Gun-powder-Treaſon was but the act of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2515:10"/>a few diſcontented Gentlemen, and the thouſand Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt in <hi>England</hi> not guilty of it; but in the preſent Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion of the Puritanes, they have ingaged a great part of that Kingdome, and many who indeed know not what the matter meanes, and ſo that this may be called the common ſinne of that Sect, whereas the other cannot be charged upon the Religion of the Papiſts.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay, it is Religion that moveth them: What? did ever the true Religion allow of rebellion? <hi>Tantum Religio potuit ſuadere malorum?</hi> I know they pretend the defence of the nationall confeſſion of their Church, and the Oath received by their forefathers in the Yeere 1581, by the Kings example and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement. But if it be ſo I will ſubſcribe their Covenant alſo, which is the greateſt curſe I can lay upon my mortall enemy. Therfore to take away that vaine pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, wherewith they blind you and many other ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple people; I will here make it evidently appeare, Firſt, that that negative Confeſſion wherunto they did ſwear in the yeere 81, is not the nationall Confeſſion of the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and Secondly, that the Oath which they have now adminiſtred is not the ſame, which the King, his Family, States, and Subjects, did ſweare at that time; But Subſtantially different from it in many points.</p>
            <p>And firſt, that Negative Confeſſion is not the nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall Confeſſion of the Church of <hi>Scotland:</hi> But the nationall Confeſſion is that, which twenty yeeres be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, being penned by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Knox,</hi> and his fellow-mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and contayning the poſitive grounds of Divinity; was approved by the Parliament held in the yeere 1560; and afterwards was ratified by a Parliament in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2515:10"/>the yeere 1567, and regiſtred in the body of that Act of Parliament, and ſo confirmed by a number of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments ſince that time. The ſame is likewiſe recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved into the body of the Confeſſions of all the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches, and acknowledged for the Confeſſion of the Church of <hi>Scotland.</hi> But as for that Negative Confeſſion, conſiſting in the abjuring of Popiſh errors, and penned by M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Craig,</hi> for the detecting of ſome diſguiſed Papiſts, who by Equivocation, or out of hope of Papall diſpenſation, did for feare of the Laws, ſubſcribe unto the former confeſſion; That negative confeſſion (I ſay) was never confirmed by any Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament. What Confirmation it had, was onely from the Kings mandate, whom they procured not only himſelfe to ſweare and ſubſcribe; but alſo to command all his Subjects to do ſo. But here I pray you to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der firſt, What age the King was of then: not full Fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen yeeres, by foure moneths. And how eaſie a matter was it to abuſe his tender youth? Let us ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore appeale from K. <hi>Iames a minor,</hi> unto himſelfe when he was of riper yeeres: And we ſhall find that he did utterly diſallow of that fact, inſomuch, that in the Parliament held the yeere 84. he procured the firſt confeſſion to be confirmed; but without any mention of the latter, and ſo in divers Parliaments following. And in the Conference at Hampton Court he did fully manifeſt his diſlike of that Negative con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, ſaying that M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Craig</hi> with his <hi>I renounce,</hi> and <hi>I deteſt,</hi> did multiply ſo many particulars, that ſimple people were not able to conceive; And ſo being ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed did either fall backe into Popery, or remaine ſtill in their ignorance: And (ſaith he) If I ſhould hold my ſelfe to that forme, the confeſſion of my faith muſt bee
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2515:11"/>in my Table-booke and not in my head. So that it hath no civill confirmation at all. But you will ſay that a Sinodicall confirmation, by a generall Aſſembly held at <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> another at <hi>Glaſgow:</hi> wherunto I anſwer, that the act of the Synod had onely relation unto the Kings mandate: For thus the words runne. <hi>Foraſmuch as the Kings Majeſtie hath ſet forth and proclaimed a Godly Confeſsion of faith — This preſent. Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly doth appoint that all Miniſters ſhall conforme them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves therunto under paine of deprivation.</hi> So that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſtrength is in the Synodicall confirmation de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon the force and vigor of the Kings mandate; while that was in force, the confirmation of the Synod was in force; and that being expired, the confirmation of the Synod is likewiſe expired: But the Kings man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date is expired, becauſe upon mature judgment hee did retract and diſallow it in his life time, and though he had not, yet the ſame being a perſonall act of the Kings without the conſent of the States of Parliament, is now certainly expired with his royall breath: For <hi>Mortuo mandatore expirat mandatum.</hi> So that indeed this Confeſſion which they now urge ſo violently up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Kings Subjects, hath no legall confirmation at all. And as it hath no confirmation, So it never had the honour to be received into the body of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions of reformed Churches, as was the former Confeſſion; neither indeed was it worthy; for it is not a Confeſſion of faith at all; but a Confeſſion of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleefe: The author tels us not what he doth beleeve, but what he doth not beleeve. And I hope you will all confeſſe, that faith conſiſts in aſſenting to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed truths, and not in diſſenting from errors. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides is it not more fit, for a Miniſter to teach his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2515:11"/>poſitive truths of Chriſtian Doctrine, then to ſpend his time in telling them of unknown hereſies?</p>
            <p>And as that Negative Confeſſion is not the nationall confeſſion of that Church, ſo the Oath that is now mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred, is not the ſame with that which was received by the Kings Majeſty and his Subjects in the yeere 81 as is pretended: But is ſubſtantially different from it in many reſpects.</p>
            <p n="1">1 In the former Oath or Covenant, they did ſwear with the King and by his commandement, and their is no doubt but it is moſt lawfull for Subjects, (if the matter of the Oath be true and Lawfull) to ſwear by the commandement of the king, to whom primarily and Originally, belongs the power to miniſter an Oath, and to others only by Commiſſion and power delega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from him: But this new Oath, is not only with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the King, but againſt him, and flat contrary to his commandement; For ſince the time that his Majeſty manifeſted his Royall pleaſure, requiring them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce their covenant, they have proceeded and ſworn many thouſands of people. So that I am ſure by the Lawes of our Kingdome they are in a great Premunire.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In the firſt Oath or Covenant, there is no bond of mutuall defence. But in this new Oath there is a bond of mutuall defence of one another, <hi>Againſt all perſons whatſoever,</hi> the King himſelfe not excepted.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Although there had been ſuch a bond of mutuall defence in the former Covenant, yet ought it not to be in this: for Subjects may lawfully make a Covenant of mutuall defence by Armes, by the conſent of the King who only hath the power of the Sword within his dominions; But they who made this late Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant had not the Kings conſent: but did it contrary to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2515:12"/>the Kings expreſſe will and pleaſure: wherein they have violated the lawes of their own kingdome which they were bound to maintaine: for by an act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>Anno</hi> 1585, all leagues or bonds of mutuall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence made without the privity and conſent of the King are expreſly forbidden. And as in this reſpect their Covenant is contrary to the Lawes of their kingdome; So I am ſure it is contrary unto the Law of God; for I never knew any Divine who doth not maintain that unto the undertaking of a juſt warre, there is required not only a good cauſe, but alſo lawfull authority. A juſt cauſe of warre doth not warrant every man to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake warre, though againſt a ſtranger, (much leſſe againſt the King, againſt whom no cauſe, though never ſo juſt, can make a warre undertaken by his Subjects warrantable) But a juſt cauſe doth only warrant the King, or ſupreme Magiſtrate, in whom authority is originally and Primarily; and without whoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion the Warres undertaken by private men, are no better then robbery and murther. That raſh and heady adventure of the Iſraelits againſt the Canaanites. <hi>Num.</hi> cap. 14. v. 44. was without authority; for neither <hi>Moſes</hi> nor the Arke went up with them: and therfore <hi>Moſes</hi> doth call their attempt a preſumption; and they proſpered accordingly, for they were ſmitten unto <hi>Hormah,</hi> a name anſwerable unto the event, namely <hi>deſtruction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> this Oath is not the ſame with the former, becauſe it contains not only the old Covenant, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion; but alſo their owne interpretation of it: For they do plainly inſinuate, that Epiſcopall government, and the 5. Articles of <hi>Perth,</hi> are abjured in that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion. Now it is reaſonable, that a few factious ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2515:12"/>who are the Authors of this conſpiracy, ſhould take upon them to interpret a Nationall confeſſion, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude their interpretation upon the whole Church, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing all men to ſweare unto it? This were too much though their interpretation were true, becauſe it wants publique authority and approbation. But indeed the interpretation is moſt notoriouſly falſe, and like the gloſſe of <hi>Orleance</hi> which deſtroyes the Text. Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall government is not abjured in the Negative con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, nor ſo much as mentioned. If any man ſhall ſay, That Epiſcopacy is included under the Popes wicked Hierarchy, which there is denied; he will prove himſelf ridiculous: for it is well known unto all that ever look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into the Eccleſiaſticall hiſtory, that the Church was governed by Biſhops, 600 yeers before the Popes wicked Hierarchy began. And as that government was not abjured, ſo neither is it any innovation at all: for it is evident that in the yeere 81. they had Biſhops, and it is yet to be ſeen regiſtrate in the Books of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, and ſubſcribed by the Commiſſioners for the time, how that but a little time before the publiſhing of that Confeſſion, the generall Aſſembly did agree with his Majeſties Regents in his minority,<note place="margin">Kings de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration.</note> that the eſtate of Biſhops (which is one of the eſtates of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) ſhould be maintained and authorized: But about foure or five yeeres after, about the yeere 83. the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Aſſembly tooke upon them, contrary to their own ſubſcriptions, to diſcharge the eſtate of Biſhops, and to declare the ſame to be unlawfull; commanding all the Biſhops in the kingdome to dimit their places and Juriſdictions, under paine of Excommunication: and in like manner commanding the King and his Councell under the like payne, not to chooſe any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb facs="tcp:2515:13"/>in their place. But when that wiſe King ſaw their proceedings, and how they took more upon them then ever the Biſhops had done; and under the pretence of their new diſcipline, trod upon his Scepter, labouring to eſtabliſh an Eccleſiaſticall tyranny of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Juriſdiction: and perceiving withall, that their new erected government was the mother of all facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, confuſion, and rebellion; And that it tended to Anabaptiſme and popularity; and to the overthrow of his State, Crowne and kingdome: 1584, he called a Parliament, and by the conſent of all his States hee overthrew their Presbytries, and reſtored againe the Biſhops to their places. But indeed at that time the Sonnes of <hi>Zerviah</hi> were too ſtrong for him that hee could never inveſt the Biſhops with their full power and authority, untill that happy time that his Majeſty came unto the Crowne of England: And then not long after by a free Generall aſſembly held at Glaſgow, he did not erect, but ratify and confirme the eſtate of Biſhops, The acts of which Aſſembly were immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately after confirmed by Act of Parliament, So that Epiſcopacy is no Innovation, as is pretended in this laſt Oath.</p>
            <p>And as for the 5. Acts of Perth Aſſembly, they were never intended to be abjured in the Negative con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion: for there is no mention of any of them; neither can they be comprehended under popiſh rites. Kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the Communion, is no popiſh rite, for I have upon another occaſion proved it to be the geſture uſed in the Primitive Church at the receiving of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; And that the firſt that ever did ſit after their faſhion was the Pope, to expreſſe his ſtate; So that we may juſtly charge them, that the geſture which
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:2515:13"/>they uſe, is abjured in that confeſſion, amongſt the reſt of popiſh rits. The Five Holy-dayes eſtabliſhed by the Aſſembly of Perth, are not Popiſh rites; but ſuch as were obſerved in the Church, ſince the dayes of the Apoſtles, as may appeare by that bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter contention, between the Eaſterne and Weſterne Churches, about the obſervation of Eaſter. And as for the other three Articles, for private Baptiſme, the Communion of the ſick, and Confirmation of Children; There is no man in his right wits who will not acknowledge that they were in uſe many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeeres before Popery was hatched; and are in themſelves things not onely lawfull and expedient, but in ſome caſes neceſſary.</p>
            <p>But yet they will ſay, that theſe things are abjured in generall termes, when they ſweare to continue in <hi>the obedience of the doctrine</hi> and <hi>diſcipline of that Kirk.</hi> For anſwer wherunto, I ſhall deſire you to conſider Firſt, that they ſay not they will continue in the <hi>preſent diſcipline of this Kirk;</hi> (as theſe new men doe interpret it) but indefinitely, that they will continue <hi>in the diſcipline of this Kirk.</hi> Secondly, albeit they had ſaid ſo; yet by the diſcipline we muſt underſtand that diſcipline, which was eſtabliſhed by authority and Law; And not that which was violently brought in by ſome factious Miniſters and their adherents. Now I have ſhewed that Epiſcopall government was ratified and confirmed by divers Acts of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; but never diſſolved by any: and that their Presbyteriall government was put down by act of Parliament; but never eſtabliſhed by any. Thirdly, ſay that by diſcipline, we ſhould yeeld to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that diſcipline which then was uſed, though
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:2515:14"/>brought in by private authority: Yet certainly it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s never their intent to ſweare to maintaine that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſcipline in all particulars without alteration or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tion: for ſuch an oath had been ſimply unlawfull; becauſe that thereby they ſhould have made a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>uall Law concerning ceremonies and rites, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> themſelves and muſt be changeable according <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Exigency of the times. And ſo if that inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>tation which is now given of the words, were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap>e, it would follow;</p>
            <p n="1">1 That their negative Confeſſion were directly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ntrary unto their poſitive Confeſſion, which is the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nly true Nationall confeſſion of the Church of Scotland; For in that confeſſion, in the 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Article, touching matters of Policy and order, they ſay: <hi>Not that we thirk that one policy and one order in Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies can be appointed for all ages, times and places: For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Ceremonies ſuch as men have deviſed are but temporall, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o may and ought they to be changed, when they rather ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer Superſition, then that they edifie the Church uſing the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ame.</hi> So that by theſe mens Interpretation, here is Confeſſion againſt Confeſſion: The poſitive Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion declares matters of Policy and order to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terable, and ſuch as upon occaſion both may and ought to be changed: But theſe men do ſo interpret the negative Confeſſion and Covenant, as if they were bound by an oath, to preſerve the ſame Orders that were uſed in the yeer 81. inviolably for ever.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Such an Interpretation is againſt all right rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; For the condition of the Church being change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, the ſame Orders cannot be convenient for her at all times: As the ſame policy is not fit for the Church in all places, ſo neither for one and the ſame Church at all times.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:2515:14"/>
            <p n="3">3 Such an Interpretation ſhall condemne the practice of the ancient Church, which did upon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion often change her rites, as namely dipping in Baptiſme, which ſhe changed from once into thrice, and again from thrice into once.</p>
            <p n="4">4 It is contrary to the Judgement of all Divines. Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> tells us that <hi>In externall diſcipline and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies Chriſt would not particularly preſcribe what we ſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> to follow, Quod iſtud pendere a temporum varieta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te pravideret.</hi> And again he ſaith, That ſometimes it profiteth and is expedient that there be a difference in theſe things, leſt men ſhould think that Religion were tyed unto outward Ceremonies. And indeed, to make the Rites of the Church unchangeable, were to confound matters of Doctrine, and matters of Diſcipline, matters of Faith, and matters of Order. The rule therefore of <hi>Tertullian</hi> is infallible; <hi>Regula fidei immobilis, irrefragabilis, Caetera diſciplinae admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunt novitatem correctionis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5 If they had ſworne (as theſe men would have it) to maintaine their diſcipline which they then u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed without alteration or addition, like the Laws of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians;</hi> Then had they aſcribed unto themſelves an abſolute perfection, more then ever did the <hi>Phariſees</hi> in Chriſts dayes, or the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> after, or the Popes of late, ſince they eſtabliſhed their own infallibility. Surely the contrivers of the firſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, did manifeſt a great deal of more modeſty in their Preface. <hi>Proteſting; that if any man ſhall note in this our Confeſsion, any Article or Sentence repugnant to Gods holy Word, and do admoniſh of the ſame in Writing, we by Gods grace do promiſe unto him ſatisfaction from the mouth of God, that is, from his holy Scriptures, or elſe,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2515:15"/>reformation of that which he ſhall prove to be amiſſe.</hi> And are theſe men become wiſer then their Fathers, to think that nothing w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> they did, could be amended?</p>
            <p n="6">6 That could not be the meaning of the firſt Oath to maintain their diſcipline in all points with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out alteration: For they themſelves during the days of the Presbytery did change many things, and that as I beleeve without violation of their Oath. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times their Lay-elders had voyce in the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, afterwards the Miniſters perceiving the inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience, reſtrained them to their Pariſh-ſeſſions: Sometimes it was made altogether unlawfull to bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in Churches; afterwards they did permit it. And if I had the inſpection of the Book of the Acts of the generall Aſſembly which I have not ſeen theſe four and twenty yeers; I would make it appear that every Aſſembly, did either alter or adde ſomething in matters of diſcipline. Finally, How could they Swear to maintain that diſcipline in all points, when there are many things in their new found diſcipline, whereof they were not agreed, nor are to this day? as namely, Whether Paſtors and Doctors be one of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, or diſtinct; And if diſtinct, Whether Doctors have any voyce in government: What is the Office of Deacons, and whether they may give a voyce in the conſiſtory with the reſt: Whether their ruling Eldermen be Eccleſiaſticall perſons or Lay-men: Whether their Office ſhould be only annuall, or du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring life: Whether thoſe Elders ſhould have a voice in the election, Ordination, deprivation of miniſters; and in weilding of the keyes for Excommunication and Abſolution.</p>
            <p>By all which it is more then manifeſt, that the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2515:15"/>meaning of theſe words in the former Oath, <hi>[We will continue in the obedience of the diſcipline of this Kirk]</hi> is not that they would obſerve the ſame diſcipline then uſed in all particulars, without alteration or additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: for ſo their Oath muſt be contrary to their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of faith, contrary to right reaſon, to the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of the Primitive Church, to the opinion of all Divines, yea, contrary to their owne practice, and indeed ſuch an Oath, as were both unlawfull and impoſſible to be obſerved. And unleſſe that Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation be allowed them, that Oath makes nothing either againſt Epiſcopacy, or the five Articles of Perth, we muſt therefore finde out ſome other mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of theſe words of the Covenant. It is a rule in the civill Law; <hi>Semper in dubijs benigniora ſunt praefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendae,</hi> And again, <hi>Non ſunt reyiciendae leges quae in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretatione aliquâ poſſunt convenire.</hi> If any thing, Fact, writing or Law may in reaſonable conſtruction admit two interpretations, the beſt and mildeſt is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to be received. But the words in the former Oath may admit a good interpretation, namely they did ſweare to continue in the diſcipline of that Kirk, in regard of all ſubſtantials, <hi>viz.</hi> for adminiſtration of the Sacraments, and weilding of the Keyes for binding and looſing of ſinners, and that for the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular determination, of perſon, time, place, and outward forme of adminiſtration; They would ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the diſcipline of that Kirk, which ſhould be from time to time lawfully eſtabliſhed. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is (as I obſerved before) that they did not ſay <hi>The preſent diſcipline of this Kirk.</hi> And by this Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation which is the only reaſonable ſenſe of theſe words that can be given; they are all bound by their
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:2515:16"/>nationall Oath, (as they terme it) to ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to Epiſcopall government, and the Articles of Perth, which were lawfully eſtabliſhed, and are now a part of the Diſcipline of that Church.</p>
            <p>Thus have I ſhewed that this late Oath is ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially different from the former: in that now they doe not ſweare with the King, but againſt him; It containes a bond of mutuall defence of one another; It inables Subjects to take Armes without lawfull Authority, and containes ſuch an interpretation of the Old covenant, as is manifeſtly falſe. In all which reſpects, the Oath is unlawfull: But yet to convince them further of perjury I will ſhew unto you, that they have not obſerved any of theſe conditions which God himſelfe requireth in an Oath. In the fourth of <hi>Ieremy</hi> and ſecond verſe: <hi>Thou ſhalt ſweare the Lord liveth, in trueth, in iudgement, and in righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe.</hi> In trueth, and therefore not falſly; In judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and therefore not raſhly: In righteouſneſſe, and therefore not lewdly nor to a bad end. We muſt ſweare in trueth and not falſly; for the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſaith, <hi>Yee ſhall not ſweare by my name falſly, Levit.</hi> 19.12. The onely true matter of an Oath is trueth, but all the grounds of this laſt Oath, are notoriouſly falſe, as namely that the Negative Confeſſion, is the Nationall confeſſion of the church of Scotland: And I have ſhewed that to be otherwiſe. That this Oath is the very ſame that King <hi>Iames</hi> and his Family did ſweare: And I have proved that not to be ſo. That Epiſcopacie and the five Articles of <hi>Perth</hi> are inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations abjured in the former Oath: and I have ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted that to be evidently falſe. Finally, That what they doe is to avert, <hi>The danger of the true refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:2515:16"/>religion, of the Kings honor, and of the publick peace of the Kingdome.</hi> When as indeed they could not have taken a courſe more to indanger the true Religion, wound the Kings honour, and diſturbe the publick peace. So that in this late <hi>Oath</hi> there is no <hi>trueth.</hi> Againe, We muſt ſweare in <hi>judgement,</hi> that is, out of a certain knowledge of the thing which we ſweare. We finde in the fifth of <hi>Leviticus,</hi> that when a man did ſweare that which was <hi>hid from him;</hi> It was a ſin for which a Treſpaſſe-offering was to be offered. And now they have ſworn unto many things which are hid from them, and whereof they could have no certaine knowledge; for they could not know that the Negative Confeſſion is the National Confeſſion of that Church; nor that this Oath is the ſame with that which the King did ſweare; nor that Epiſcopacy and the five Articles of <hi>Perths Aſſembly</hi> were abjured in the former Oath: For I have evidently proved all theſe to be falſe. Beſides, in the Catalogue of errors renounced, there are many things wich com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people cannot underſtand, as namely, I would gladly know, how many amongſt that multitude who have ſworn this late Covenant, doe know what is <hi>Opus operatum,</hi> abjured in the Oath. It is wiſely provided in the civill Law, that none ſhould be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to ſweare, who are not of ſome reaſonable underſtanding, and therfore no Idiots, nor mad men, nor children are admitted to be witneſſes: But in this laſt Oath they have ſworn many thouſands who have not ſo much knowledge of an Oath, of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or of the confeſſion of Faith; as a child of ſeven yeere old. And therefore they doe not ſweare in <hi>Iudicio.</hi> Laſtly, as we muſt ſweare in trueth, and in
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:2515:17"/>judgement, ſo alſo in <hi>righteouſneſſe:</hi> As the matter of our Oath muſt be true, and our knowledge of it cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine: So we muſt ſweare unto a good and lawfull end: For to make the name of God a bond to doe evill, is a ſinne out of meaſure ſinfull. But the end of this laſt Oath is moſt unlawfull, even to arme Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects againſt their Prince, and pull downe Orders eſtabliſhed by Lawes, wherby they make that which ſhould be <hi>Sacramentum pietatis,</hi> to be <hi>Vinculum ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitatis.</hi> Theſe Oaths vve call <hi>Juramenta latronum,</hi> ſuch as theeves and robbers take to be true one to another: For they doe not only joyne hand in hand (as <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us) but doe even alſo by Oath bind themſelves to doe miſchiefe.<note place="margin">Prov. 11.2. Nehem. 6.18.</note> 
               <hi>Tobiah</hi> the greateſt hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer of the Temple, had many in <hi>Judah</hi> his ſworne men. Further, as they have not ſworne neither in trueth, in judgement, nor in righteouſneſſe: So there are many who have ſworne this Oath, who before did receive the Oath of the Kings Supremacie, and of Canonicall obedience, and conformity to the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of <hi>Perth:</hi> So that here is Oath againſt Oath. Belike theſe men doe challenge a <hi>Papall</hi> power to diſpence with Oathes. All theſe things being conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, I have diſcovered as much perjurie in their Oath, as can be committed in a promiſſorie Oath. And then wee know that the rule in Divinity is, <hi>Paenitenda promiſsio, non perficienda praeſumptio.</hi> And ſurely ſince this is a ſwearing age with them, they may doe well to ſweare once more, that they will never ſweare ſo againe. When <hi>David</hi> had made a raſh Oath to deſtroy <hi>Nabal,</hi> in cold blood he did chooſe rather to breake his Oath then to keepe it. And I think there is no Divine who will not ſay, that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2515:17"/>
               <hi>Herod</hi> had better broken his raſh oath, then cut off <hi>Iohn Baptiſts</hi> head. And yet I muſt tell you, it is not altogether ſo haynous a crime to take a head from a Prophet, as to pull a Crowne from a Kings head.</p>
            <p>And now have I taken from them all pretence of Religion, (which is not fit to make a cloake for ſuch knavery) by ſhewing that the Negative confeſſion, is not the Nationall Confeſſion of the Church of Scotland; and that this Oath is not the ſame which was ſworne <hi>An.</hi> 81. but an Oath in many reſpects al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together unlawfull: And finally, that Epiſcopall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and the Articles of <hi>Perth</hi> are not abjured in the Negative Confeſſion. I will now gueſſe what are the true cauſes that ſet them on work, not uſing light conjectures, but building upon more then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable grounds.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That which ſets the <hi>Clergie</hi> on work is <hi>Selfe-love,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De civit. Dei Lib. 14. cap. 28.</note> which (as S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſayes) did build the Citie of the devill. It is pride, ſingularity, ambition, and the deſire of popular applauſe. They cannot endure to be ſubject to a Biſhop, eſteeming themſelves men of greater gifts and perfections, then thoſe who are appointed to be their Biſhops, and ſo <hi>They periſh in the gaine-ſaying of Core.</hi> You know that <hi>Core</hi>'s ſinne was diſobedience: he would not be ſubject unto <hi>Aaron</hi> appointed his Superiour by God, nor to <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> either who ſwayed the Scepter: So they by their good will, will not be ſubject either to Biſhop or King. This pride hath beene the occaſion of many hereſies in the Church, as will evidently appeare un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe who read the Hiſtories of <hi>Arius</hi> coveting the Biſhoprick of <hi>Alexandria:</hi> of <hi>Donatus</hi> labouring to have beene Biſhop of <hi>Carthage:</hi> of <hi>Novatus</hi> deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:2515:18"/>a Biſhoprick in <hi>Italy:</hi> and of <hi>Aerius</hi> contending with <hi>Euſtathius</hi> for a Biſhoprick in <hi>Pontus.</hi> Theſe men affecting theſe honorable places, and receiving their ſeverall foyles, when through ambition they could not get the places they ſought for in the Church, they laboured to gaine honour another way in their ſeverall Synagogues. So I could tell you of a man, who is now a ring-leader of the faction in <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> and hath publickly preached the King to be a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt, and when his Majeſtie deſired them to renounce their Covenant, promiſing them all reaſonable ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction in other things: he in a Sermon compared his Majeſtie unto an Italian who promiſed mercy to his vanquiſhed enemie, upon a condition that he would renounce Chriſt, which when the Caitiff had done, preſently ſtabb'd him to the heart, ſaying, I hope now I have killed you both ſoule and body. Yet this man within theſe two yeeres was an earneſt ſuter for the Biſhoprick of <hi>Argyle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">M<hi rend="sup">•</hi>. Henry Rollocke.</note> and was recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended for it by many of the Biſhops of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; but miſſing thereof, the ſame humor which poſſeſſed <hi>Arius, Donatus,</hi> and the reſt, doth now alſo work in him.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That which ſets the Lay-men on work, is cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe: amongſt whom not a few would gladly prey upon the Biſhopricks, as their Fathers did upon the Abbeyes. This was obſerved by M. <hi>Cartwright,</hi> and the Author of the Eccleſiaſticall diſcipline of their Lay-followers in England; And, (I muſt needs think that they of Scotland, as they are of the ſame religion, ſo they are of the ſame mind) Whileſt they heare us ſpeak againſt Biſhops and Cathedrall Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,<note place="margin">Diſcipl. Eccleſ.</note> (ſaith the Author of the Eccleſiaſticall diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline)
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:2515:18"/>it tickleth their eares, looking for the like prey they had before of Monaſteries: Yea, they have in their hearts devoured already the Churches inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance. They care not for Religion, ſo they may get the ſpoile. They could be content to crucifie Chriſt, ſo they might have his garments. Our age is full of ſpoiling Souldiers, and of wicked <hi>Dyoniſians,</hi> who will rob Chriſt of his golden coat, as neither fit for him in Winter nor Summer. They are Cormorants, and ſeek to fill the bottomleſſe ſacks of their greedy appetites. They doe yawne after a prey, and would thereby to their perpetuall ſhame, purchaſe to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a field of blood.</p>
            <p n="3">3 I may more then probably conjecture that they have another ayme, even ſuch as was <hi>Ieroboams</hi> ayme: When he had drawne away the ten Tribes from the houſe of <hi>David,</hi> he ſaid in his heart If the people goe up to Ieruſalem to worſhip, their heart will returne againe unto their Lord <hi>Rehoboam;</hi> And therefore he erected two golden Calves, and ſaid unto the people, It is too farre for you to go up to Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem: Theſe are the gods that brought you up out of the land of Egypt. So thoſe men intending to draw away the Kings Subjects from their Obedience, and perceiving that if they ſhould joyne with his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties good Subjects, in the true and orderly wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, that their heart would returne againe unto their Lord the King: They have deviſed an Idol of their owne brain, like <hi>Ioroboams</hi> Calves, even their Presbyteriall diſcipline, and cry that up as the only true worſhip of God.</p>
            <p>And yet I hold not them all to be alike guilty; but that many of them, yea the farre greateſt part, have
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2515:19"/>not as yet learned <hi>the deepneſſe of Sathan.</hi> We may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh them into three degrees. The firſt ſort, are they who have contrived the plot, are the ring leaders of the faction, the ſeducers of others, and ſo dogma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing heretiques. For theſe I can make no excuſe; but leave them as wilde Aſſes to be ſpoken within the moneth of their affliction. The ſecond ſort, and the far greateſt number,<note place="margin">2. Sam, 15.11.</note> are thoſe who have been ſeduced by them, like thoſe Two Hundered who followed <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolon</hi> out of Jeruſalem knowing nothing of his Treaſon. They have been drawne to dance after their pipe, though they underſtood not the Spring; and have been carried head-long with it, before they knew well what they did: And all under Godly pretences. For they were made to beleeve that the very ſtate of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, Church, and Kingdome; did depend upon this New Covenant, and that all men were bound in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, to defend the Nationall confeſſion of faith, and the Oath ſworne by their forefathers. Beſides it is a plauſible matter with the people to heare them de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praved, that are in authority; but eſpecially to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand of any liberty or power, which may appertaine unto themſelves. Furthermore alſo it is not unknowne to any of Judgement, how much the profesſion of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary zeale, and as it were contempt of the world; doth worke with the multitude. When they ſee men goe ſimply in the ſtreets, and bow down their heads like a bull-ruſh, though their inward parts burne altogether with deceit, wringing their necks awry: ſhaking their heads, as though they were in ſome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent griefe: lifting up the white of their eyes ſometimes, at the ſight of ſome vanity, as they walke, when they heare them give great groanes: Cry out againſt this
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2515:19"/>ſinne and that ſinne, (not in them their hearers, but in their Superiors) and finally, make long prayers, (under colour whereof they devoure not onely the houſes of Widdowes but of married folkes too) When, I ſay the multitude do heare and ſee ſuch kind of men; They are by and by carried away with a marvellous great conceit and opinion of them, and with ſuch ſhewes have theſe Phariſaicall teachers drawne the multitude after them, who have not their ſences exerciſed to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne between good and evill: but judge onely by the outward appearance. If they ſhould judge them by their fruits; they ſhould find them to be very farre from the true Religion. S. <hi>Iames</hi> hath given us a moſt full deſcription of the true religion.<note place="margin">Iam. 3.17</note> 
               <hi>The wiſdome that is from above, is firſt pure, then peaceable, Gentle, and eaſie to be intreated, full of mercy, and good fruits, without judging, and without hypocriſie.</hi> Whereas <hi>Solomon</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes wiſedome to have built her a houſe with ſeven pillars: So the Apoſtle deſcribes this heavenly wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, (which is the true Religion) by ſeaven proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, neither of which will agree with their religion. It is not Pure; For therfore is the true religion called pure becauſe it alloweth of nothing which is not in it ſelfe juſt, lawfull, and honeſt. And hereby <hi>Lactantius</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth againſt the Gentiles, the verity of the Chriſtian religion. But their Religion alloweth of many things, which in themſelves are neither Juſt, lawfull, nor ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, as namely, <hi>Vſury, Sacriledge,</hi> diſobedience to lawfull authority, and rebellion againſt Princes. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>is not peaceable;</hi> for theſe men are the incendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aries of Chriſtendome, as if they had come to ſet fire upon the Earth. <hi>Not gentle,</hi> For they are more auſtere in their carriage, then ever was <hi>Cato.</hi> Not <hi>Eaſie to bee
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:2515:20"/>intreated;</hi> for they will neither be perſwaded by their friends, nor commanded by their ſuperiors, to doe any thing, but what they will, ſquaring themſelves by that old rule of the <hi>Do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atiſts, Quod volumus ſanctum eſt.</hi> Not <hi>full of mercy and good fruits:</hi> For they are all for ſacrifice, nothing for mercy; All for the duties of the firſt Table, neglecting the duties of the ſecond: Their faith hath drowned their charity: For we have knowne them pull downe many Churches, and yet build but a few Hoſpitalls. <hi>Not without Judging:</hi> For of all men living they are known to be the moſt ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gid cenſurers of others. And conſequently they are not without Hypocriſie: For that is the true note of an hypocrite when one, (as our Saviour ſaith) can ſpy the mote that is in his brothers eye, and not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the beame that is in his own. And yet with their pretence of piety they have deceived a number of ſimple people. But there is yet a third ſort, who have ſubſcribed the Covenant againſt their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, onely for fear of a Maſſacre, which they had juſt cauſe to ſuſpect, when a Catalogue was taken up of the names, what in every Pariſh, of thoſe who refuſed to ſubſcribe. And now, I pray you, what is become of their plea of Chriſtian liberty? For when we did preſſe them to conforme themſelves unto the Orders of our Church, they alleaged that it was contrary to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian liberty to inforce men to the doing of any thing againſt their conſcience, and that a man ſhould be fully reſolved in his owne mind of the lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of that which hee doth. And yet we did urge men onely under payne of ſuſpenſion and Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication; and that after much patience and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:2515:20"/>uſing withall all fair meanes to perſwade them. But they compell men to ſubſcribe with them againſt their Conſcience, by Pike and Piſtoll, threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning no leſſe unto the refuſers then loſſe of life, goods, and lands. By this ye may judge of the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of their actions, and what they would doe in other places, if they ſhould once gaine the power into their own hands.</p>
            <p>All this paines have I taken, to detect theſe men and their proceedings, to the end that I might draw you off from their faction: For who would be in love with that Religion, whoſe bond is Perjury, whoſe badge is Rebellion? Therefore, come out from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them and ſeparate your ſelves; Be not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker with them in their ſins, leſt you receive alſo of their plagues. Manifeſt your diſlike of them &amp; their proceedings, by conforming your ſelves abſolutely unto the Orders of this Church in all things, and think not to halt any longer between God and Baal; Neither be afraid of their power; for howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they proſper for a time: It is but a Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſtorme, <hi>Nubecula eſt &amp; cito pertranſibit:</hi> You may aſſure your ſelves that in end they will not prevaile:<note place="margin">1 Sam. 2.10</note> 
               <hi>For that God</hi> by whom Kings reigne <hi>will give ſtrength unto his King, and exalt the horme of his anoynted:</hi> He will ſcatter the people that delight in Warre, even make the hearts of the Canaanites to melt, and their joynts to tremble:<note place="margin">Pſal. 91.16.</note> 
               <hi>But will ſatisfie the King with long life, and ſhew him his ſalvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now I have wearied both you and my ſelf with a long Speech. I know there are many here who thinke I have ſpoke too much; But I could not have ſaid leſſe, and manifeſt my fidelity to God and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2515:21"/>the King. And if it be true which is grown unto a Proverb, that <hi>Leves loquuntur curae, ingentes ſtu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent:</hi> No man can expect that my Speech ſhould be elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent: For I proteſt before God, that I have ſpoken out of the grief of my heart, and the very anguiſh of my Soul. When I conſider the fearfull afterclaps that are likely to enſue: It fears me, that our ſinnes are come unto a full Maturity, and that we are ripe for Gods Sickle to reap us. I dare not ſay with S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul,</hi> that I could wiſh my ſelfe <hi>Anathema,</hi> or ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from Chriſt for my Country-men: But I can ſay with a ſincere heart, that I could be content, my life were given in a Sacrifice, ſo that could procure the peace of the Church, redeem his Majeſties honor, which is ſo deeply wounded, and preſerve my native Country from deſtruction. And therefore I beſeech all you who bear good will unto Sion, that you would apply all your indeavours, for quenching of this fire; eſpecially labouring to reclaim them who are committed to your charge: <hi>And of ſome have Compaſsion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iude verſ. 22.23.</note> 
               <hi>making a difference: and others ſave with fear: Pulling them out of the Fire.</hi> And let all of us be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant with God in Prayer, lifting up our hearts and our hands to the heavens, and beſeeching him who is the Author of peace, and lover of Concord, that he would be pleaſed to open the eyes of that people, and turne their hearts, that they may acknowledge their duty to God, and to his Vice-gerent. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:2515:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
